# Sai Puneeth Chinnam

Boston, MA | +1 (508)-315-7391

chinnam.saipuneeth@gmail.com |https://puneeth-chinnam.github.io/Portfolio/ | https://www.linkedin.com/in/puneethchinnam/

#### **SUMMARY**

Data Analyst with a master's in Data Analytics Engineering and 3 years of experience across Finance and Supply Chain sectors. Experience in performing Customer Analytics, Automating reports, and Forecasting. Expertise in trend identification from large datasets and dashboard creation.

#### **TECHNICAL SKILLS**

**Languages:** SQL, Python, R **Database:** MySQL, Oracle, RDS

Business Intelligence Tools: Tableau, Microsoft Excel, Power BI

Cloud Technologies: AWS (Athena, QuickSight, Glue, RedShift, Lambda)

Certifications: AWS Cloud Practitioner, Big Data Analytics – IBM

#### **WORK EXPERIENCE**

## **Data Analytics Coop – Supply Chain Logistics**

10/2022 - 01/2023

Schneider Electric, Franklin, TN

- Developed a Python application integrating cross-functional teams' data to automate the allocation of Orders and Inventory data, reducing 96% human hours
- Reduced daily report generation time by 70% by implementing ETL data pipelines to build sales data report using AWS Glue, integrating S3 buckets and Tableau
- Forecasted the Bill of Lading (BOL) using the Seasonal ARIMA and Prophet statistical models on time series data with 87% accuracy for the subsequent quarter
- Decreased the Forecast BIAS using hypothesis testing(t-test) of parameters and Error analysis
- Led order retrieval from SAP transactions using **SQL** queries, cleaned complex data ensuring data validation with macros using VBA, improving data access and processing time

## **Data Analyst – Advanced Customer Analytics**

06/2019 - 07/2021

Cognizant Technology Solutions, Bangalore, INDIA

- Collaborated with credit analytics team in analyzing Delinquency Rate, DTI, and Credit Score metrics to improve credit models and risk rating system's accuracy, saving 300k annually
- Performed statistical analysis to evaluate marketing strategies, validate hypotheses, and measure impact, improving CSAT, Churn Rate, and Contact Rate by 18% quarterly
- Conducted over 10 ad hoc analyses on underperforming KPI metrics using SQL to discover new insights, and patterns and presented recommendations to stakeholders
- Created reports and drill-down dashboards in Tableau, providing data-centric consulting for the clients and stakeholders based on their requirements to analyze business needs
- Owned data collection and processing of the Qualitative metrics, and BPI metrics data on Excel
  employing V-Lookup, Pivot tables, and Conditional formatting features

## Data Analyst Intern - Sustainability Analytics

01/2019 - 05/2021

Cognizant Technology Solutions, Hyderabad, INDIA

- Compiled exploratory data analyses on **quantitative and qualitative data** utilizing historical data from sensors in agricultural fields, **reducing water consumption by 28%**
- Improved a supervised learning model accuracy for consideration parameters such as water stress index, pH, and temperature, resulting in a 30% increase in agricultural productivity
- Generated dashboards using **PowerBI** to interpret and analyze data efficiently for the predictions and providing **quantitative findings** for stakeholders and business partners

10/2022 01/2023

# Sai Puneeth Chinnam

#### **ACADEMIC PROJECTS**

## Data Visualization Project - Covid-19 Impact on NYC Transit - Link

- Compiled complex data sets for subways and buses from the official MTA website, ride-hailing services data from the NYC TLC, and obtained air quality data from the US EPA data source
- Constructed four **data narratives** on **ridership trends**, the surge in food delivery, traffic volume and emissions, and the prevalence of electric vehicles on the road
- Designed an **interactive dashboard** comprising three page views featuring **14 visualizations** incorporating moving averages, parameters, annotations, and **custom-calculated fields**

## Machine Learning Project - Energy Consumption Prediction - Link

- Analyzed energy consumption patterns in buildings using 40 million data points, employing advanced predictive analytics. Conducted feature engineering to identify the critical factors
- Enforced regression analyses using eXtreme Gradient Boosting (XGBoost), CatBoost, and Linear Regression Models and tuned hyperparameters, achieving an RMSLE of 1.2
- Developed a presentation illustrating the effectiveness of **sustainable techniques** rooted in environmental factors, resulting in a **25% reduction in energy consumption**

### **EDUCATION**

## Master of Science, Data Analytics Engineering

Northeastern University, Boston, MA

Coursework: Data Mining, AWS, Operations Research, Data Visualization, Database Management

# **Bachelor of Technology, Electronics and Computer Science**

Jawaharlal Nehru Technological University, Hyderabad, India

Coursework: Big Data Analytics, Business Intelligence, Mathematics, ERP, Probability and Statistics